<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cavaliers thanks-giving. Written by a sober cavalier, T.H.</title>
            <author>T. H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1087_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867289</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867289</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 162:E1087[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cavaliers thanks-giving. Written by a sober cavalier, T.H.</title>
                  <author>T. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.C. for the Author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Royalists --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CAVALIERS Thanks-giving.</p>
            <p>Written by a Sober Cavalier, T. H.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. C.</hi> for the Author 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:119595:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119595:2"/>
            <head>THE CAVALIERS Thankſgiving.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Royal King <hi>Charls</hi> the Second's come home in peace</l>
               <l>God bleſſe his Royal Grace,</l>
               <l>And grant that we may thankfull be</l>
               <l>in our ſucceeding Race.</l>
               <l>The mighty force, his enemies all,</l>
               <l>God did them over Rule;</l>
               <l>And called a ſmall Army out of the North</l>
               <l>that ſoon their force did quell.</l>
               <l>Let men therefore before the Lord</l>
               <l>confeſſe his goodneſſe then,</l>
               <l>And ſhew the wonders he hath wrought</l>
               <l>before the Sons of men.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119595:3"/>
               <l>Gods children of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>did weep with many a tear,</l>
               <l>And ſent ſtrong prayers up to Heaven,</l>
               <l>and God their vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce did hear,</l>
               <l>But would not grant them their requeſt,</l>
               <l>until his wiſdom ſaw it good,</l>
               <l>Then he reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or'd moſt joyfully</l>
               <l>the Race of Royal blood.</l>
               <l>Let men therefore before the Lord,</l>
               <l>confeſſe his goodneſſe then,</l>
               <l>And ſhew the wonders that he doth</l>
               <l>before the Sons of men.</l>
               <l>King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, the greateſt Martyr</l>
               <l>that ever theſe Lands had bred,</l>
               <l>The wicked Traytors and malicious men,</l>
               <l>did take away his head.</l>
               <l>Wiſe men and good did then fore-ſee</l>
               <l>great wrong that they would do,</l>
               <l>To all their neighbours every where</l>
               <l>and to other Lands alſo.</l>
               <l>Grave Reverend Biſhops they diſgraced,</l>
               <l>and godly Doctors too,</l>
               <l>They put them quite out of their place</l>
               <l>and plundered them alſo.</l>
               <l>The godly prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>they did ſoon put down,</l>
               <l>And maintaind Falſe teachers every where,</l>
               <l>like Locuſts on the ground,</l>
               <l>And then they thought themſelves moſt ſure</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Balaams</hi> wicked hire,</l>
               <l>But the gates of Hell could not prevail</l>
               <l>to ſet Gods Church a fire.</l>
               <l>God will preſerve his Church be ſure, as he hath promiſe made</l>
               <l>From lewd men and unjuſt,</l>
               <l>If that we ſerve him faithfully,</l>
               <l>and in him put our truſt.</l>
               <l>Let men therefore before the Lord</l>
               <l>confeſſe his goodneſs then,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119595:3"/>
               <l>And ſhew the wonders that he doth</l>
               <l>before the ſons of men.</l>
               <l>Great ſpoyl theſe Traytors here did make,</l>
               <l>in <hi>England</hi> every where,</l>
               <l>The Scottiſh Lords could not abide</l>
               <l>but came away with fear,</l>
               <l>They plundred many, and ſequeſtred</l>
               <l>like Villains void of grace,</l>
               <l>The Engliſh Lords and Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>were f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rct out of their place.</l>
               <l>Stately houſes and Caſtles ſtrong</l>
               <l>were pulld down to the ground,</l>
               <l>They were forced for to fly,</l>
               <l>with their true heart ſo ſound.</l>
               <l>Their loyal hearts God did regard</l>
               <l>which they to the King did bear,</l>
               <l>And at the laſt God brought him home again</l>
               <l>to live in love without fear,</l>
               <l>Let men therefore before the Lord,</l>
               <l>confeſs his goodneſi then,</l>
               <l>And ſhew his kindneſs that he doth,</l>
               <l>For them the Sons of men.</l>
               <l>A cruel war theſe Rebels then,</l>
               <l>in <hi>England</hi> then did maintain,</l>
               <l>Againſt all right and reaſon then</l>
               <l>Like to blood-thirſty men.</l>
               <l>They made ſuch tumults every where.</l>
               <l>through deceit, lying and fraud,</l>
               <l>As did amaze men for to ſee,</l>
               <l>their couſening lying trade.</l>
               <l>Great Companys of armed men,</l>
               <l>and rude youth to <hi>Lambeth</hi> houſe did come,</l>
               <l>They forced the houſe in wicked ſort,</l>
               <l>till ſome were quite undone.</l>
               <l>Theſe wicked Rebels and Traytors uſed</l>
               <l>Such tricks, that Citizens down did go,</l>
               <l>Unto <hi>White-hall</hi> with Petitions as thick as moats in Sun</l>
               <l>for to procure their own wo.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119595:4"/>
               <l>Such doings then my eyes did ſee,</l>
               <l>I thought they all had been mad,</l>
               <l>They kept Centry at every croſſe way</l>
               <l>alas it was too bad.</l>
               <l>They ſo deluded plain ſimple men,</l>
               <l>that thouſands out did go,</l>
               <l>With Spades and Shovels and Swords by their ſide</l>
               <l>for to procure their own wo.</l>
               <l>They went out with great Companys every day</l>
               <l>with Drums ſounding Dub a dub dub,</l>
               <l>They carryed out Victuals and wrought for nothing</l>
               <l>thinking themſelves in fools Paradice ſure as a club.</l>
               <l>They made great ditches and caſt up great Mounts,</l>
               <l>to keep out their beſt friend,</l>
               <l>Such blind zeale on them did grow,</l>
               <l>being falſly uſherred in,</l>
               <l>And many a Knave grew out of this duſt</l>
               <l>which did ſhew their teeth and grin,</l>
               <l>And ſay, if they knew who were Cavaliers,</l>
               <l>they would ſtrip them all to the skin.</l>
               <l>Our Warres did very much encreaſe</l>
               <l>in <hi>England</hi> every where,</l>
               <l>The Rebels they did grow ſo proud</l>
               <l>without any grace or fear.</l>
               <l>Some Victories to the Cavaliers</l>
               <l>God did them freely give,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Branford</hi> and in <hi>Cornwell</hi> too,</l>
               <l>Which did their hearts relieve.</l>
               <l>Great mercy there our King did ſhew,</l>
               <l>as did appear moſt plain,</l>
               <l>Which made all them that had any grace</l>
               <l>againſt themſelves complain.</l>
               <l>But the wicked Rebels ſtill perſue,</l>
               <l>their malice, ſpight and wrong,</l>
               <l>Untill ſuch time that they deſerved,</l>
               <l>the hate of God and man.</l>
               <l>The Nations they ſtood looking on,</l>
               <l>and wondring at our wo,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119595:4"/>
               <l>They ſaid we <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> were mad</l>
               <l>and knew not what to do.</l>
               <l>The factious people brought their Plat:</l>
               <l>and made a mighty Maſſe,</l>
               <l>As freely as the Idolatrous <hi>Jewes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>did make a golden Calf;</l>
               <l>But now the name of God be prayſ'd,</l>
               <l>our people are wiſer grown.</l>
               <l>They will no more ſo cheated be</l>
               <l>of that which is their own.</l>
               <l>But now the hearts of moſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>is cleared from this thing.</l>
               <l>Both Cavaliers and ſober Presbytiers,</l>
               <l>will ſay God ſave our <hi>KING.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Noble men, Knights and Colonels,</l>
               <l>and Citizens high and low,</l>
               <l>Moſt joyfully proclaim'd our King,</l>
               <l>in <hi>London</hi> in triumph did go.</l>
               <l>And other Citys and Towns in theſe three Kingdoms all,</l>
               <l>Great joy they did expreſſe,</l>
               <l>With naked Swords within their hand</l>
               <l>to ſhew their readineſſe.</l>
               <l>Great ſhouls of joy within the ſtreets,</l>
               <l>did eccho to the Sky,</l>
               <l>Saying, God ſave our Royal King</l>
               <l>and bleſſe his Majeſty.</l>
               <l>The Son and Heir of our beloved Martyr'd King</l>
               <l>which dyed to do us good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>With Faith, hope, and Patience he did fore-ſee</l>
               <l>that God would do him good,</l>
               <l>And receive his ſoul into Heaven,</l>
               <l>and bleſſe his Royall ſeed alſo,</l>
               <l>And that God would in his due time</l>
               <l>All his enemies overthrow.</l>
               <l>All thanks be unto God on high</l>
               <l>which hath performed this great thing,</l>
               <l>And ſent home his Son to be our guide,</l>
               <l>A wiſe and godly <hi>King.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119595:5"/>
               <l>By whom we may have great hopes of Peace</l>
               <l>and I ove ſo to abound,</l>
               <l>At home, abroad and every where</l>
               <l>throughout the world ſo round.</l>
               <l>The Nations they will ſay abroad,</l>
               <l>God hath not <hi>England</hi> forſook,</l>
               <l>For he hath ſent them home their Royal King</l>
               <l>For to do them all good.</l>
               <l>Let men therefore before the Lord,</l>
               <l>confeſſe his goodneſs then,</l>
               <l>And ſhew the wonders that he doth</l>
               <l>before the ſons of men.</l>
               <l>Let men whom God redeemed hath</l>
               <l>give thanks unto his name,</l>
               <l>And ſhew how they from foes were freed</l>
               <l>and how God wrought the ſame.</l>
               <l>That nine and twenty day of <hi>May;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>which did the tydings bring</l>
               <l>Of Peace, let all men keep and ſay</l>
               <l>With me,</l>
               <closer>GOD ſave the KING.</closer>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
